The Gemara of today's דף daf is קייז Kuf Yud Zayin 117.
We're a little behind, but not as behind as we were before.
We pick up on קטז Kuf Tet Vav עמוד ב Amud Bet
about 20 lines down. It's line תוספות Tosafot הספנים, Hassafanim, and we're
dealing with different types of practices of
donkey drivers and sailors and so on when something has to be
done to save the ship, how do you distribute the cost. So
it says that if it's an issue about casting off the weight,
so you distribute it based on the different weight of the cargo
that everybody has brought on board. And now it says ובלבד שלא
ישנו ממנהג הספנים, u’vilvad shelo yeshanu miminhag hassafanim, but not to change
from the normal practice among sailors or a ship owner. ורשאין הספנים,
Verasha’in hassafanim, and the ship owners are allowed להתנות, lehatnot, to stipulate,
שכל מי שאבדה לו ספינה, shekol mi she’avda lo sefina, anybody who
loses a ship, supposedly they went in like a convoy of ships
to do some trade or whatever they were doing, and so if
one person's ship gets lost, because those things happen on a regular
basis, so rather than it just being that person's bad luck, they
all will share in the
responsibility and therefore יעמידו לו ספינה אחרת, ya’amidu lo sefina acheret, they
will replace his ship. אבדה לו בכוסיא, Avda lo bekusya, however, if
it was lost in, even though they say that, implicit or what
we should assume are the parameters are, that if it's lost in
negligence, אין מעמידין, ein ma’amidin, then you would not replace. שלא בכוסיא,
Shelo bekusya, not with negligence, מעמידין לו, ma’amidin lo, you do replace.
ואם פירש למקום שאין הספינות הולכין, Ve’im perash lemakom she’ein hassefinot holchin,
and let's say this one guy, he took his ship and he
went to a place or boat or whatever ship, I think makes
you think of like the Queen Elizabeth, if he took his boat
to a place where it's not normally where the other boats were
going, the not normal route, then אין מעמידין, ein ma’amidin, so then
you do not replace. That's seen as a type of a negligence,
or maybe it's seen as he's breaking off from the group and
part of the idea is that you're that it's replacing is because
you're part of the group.
So Gemara says פשיטא, pishita, obviously that that's not part of the
deal. לא צריכא דבניסן מרחקי חד אשלא, lo tzricha devenisan marchaki chad
ashla, the case would be that in Nisan where the water runs
very high because the waters in the river whatever are coming off
from the melted snow so there's a very high water level, so
people are only one unit away from the edge of the shore.
ובתישרי מרחקי תרי אשלי, uvtishrei marchaki trei ashlei, and in Tishrei they
distance themselves two where the water level is lower, they distance themselves
two units away from the shore. והאי אזל ביומי
ניסן למקום תשרי, vehai azal beyomei nisan lemakom tishrei, and this ship
is going in, it's the Nisan, it's the spring where the ships
are normally sailing closer to the shore and it's going more in
the center of the river where the ships go when it's in
the wintertime,
למקום תשרי. lemakom tishrei. So he is going to a place that's
not where the other ships are going, but it is a normal
place where ships go at a different season. So in that case,
מהו דתימא, mahu deteima, I might have thought
דאורחיה נקט ואזיל, de’orchei nakat ve’azil, it's just
following its habit, I mean, I once was asking somebody for directions
where to go
somewhere and I was borrowing their car and it was a place
that they went like I said how do you get to this
shopping list, just go in the car it'll know where to go.
So anyway,
maybe the ship just knows where to go because it goes there
all the time. Anyway the point is that it's not crazy, it's
a normal place where the ships go except not during this time
of year. קא משמע לן ka mashma lan that no, that's not
an excuse. In this time people are the ships are closer to
the shore and if you go further from the shore then it's
negligence and your ship does not get replaced. So the Gemara, תנו
רבנן, tanu rabanan, now we taught.
Do you think it's possible Rashi's reading in European like realities? I
mean like in Babylonia, the שלגים shlagim are really melting?
Yeah, I mean the Gemara discussed it all the time by מקוה
mikva concerns or whatever. I mean I think that's a regular constant
that the water level in rivers goes up significantly in the spring
because of melted snow. תנו רבנן. tanu rabanan. שיירא שהייתה מהלכת במדבר,
shayara shehayita mehalechet bamidbar, a caravan that was going in the wilderness,
ועמד גייס וטרפה, ve’amad gayis utrafa, and some troops came and it
plundered it, ועמד אחד מהם והציל, ve’amad echad mehem vehitzil, and one
guy got up and he decided that he was going to take
on the troops and he managed to save the caravan. הציל לאמצע,
hitzil le’emtza, so then it doesn't like, oh I saved it, I
get to keep all of the wealth of the caravan because otherwise
it would have been taken. No, it gets equally distributed, it still
belongs to all the owners of the caravan even though you did
a wonderful thing and you saved it for all of us. ואם
אמר אני אציל לעצמי, ve’im amar ani atzil le’atzmi, but he says
I'm going to stand up and I'm going to fight off these
troops but anything I save I'm keeping for myself, then הציל לעצמו,
hitzil le’atzmo, it works, he gets to keep it for himself. So
Gemara says what's the logic here? היכי דמי, heichi dami, what's the
case? אי יכול להציל, iy yachol lehatzil, if it's type of a
money that could be that everybody else they could put forth the
effort and they could fight off the caravan and save it, so
it's not yet הפקר hefker because it can be still saved, it's
seen as salvageable. for myself then הציל עצמו hitzil atzmo it works
he gets to keep it for himself. So then the Gemara says
what's the logic here? היכי דמי heichi dami what's the case? אי
יכול להציל ee yachol lehatzil if it's type of a money that
could be that everybody else they could put forth the effort and
they could fight off the caravan and save it, so it's not
yet הפקר hefker because it could be still saved. It's seen as
salvageable, that's what we've been discussing until now. And then the stuff
is not considered הפקר. hefker. So in that case אפילו צווח ואמר
ליה afilu tzavach ve'amar lei who cares what he says? The stuff
still belongs to the owners, it was salvageable, so he did the
nice thing, he did it all by himself, but it belongs to
the original owners. He doesn't get to keep it. ולא יכול להציל,
v'lo yachol lehatzil, if it wasn't salvageable and he did some great
act of bravery but under normal circumstances it wasn't, then it's automatically
הפקר. hefker. And אפילו רישא נמי לעצמו, afilu reisha nami le'atzmo, even
if he doesn't say anything, he should be allowed to keep it.
אמר רמי בר חמא הכא בשותפי עסקינן. amar Rami bar Chama hacha
b'shutafei maskinan. We're talking about partners, okay? So it's they both jointly
own the property, okay? וכגון זה, u'chagon zeh, now what, so then
how does it, how is it relevant what he says? שותף חולק
שלא לדעת חבירו. shutaf cholek shelo l'da'at chaveiro. In these types of
circumstances, one partner can basically say without the guy agreeing, you know
what, I'm leaving the partnership, like we're about to be attacked or
whatever, I'm operating for myself. For myself, I am sort of separating
from the partnership. So how does that work? אמר פלי. amar palli.
If he basically says, I'm going to save it for myself, then
basically, that
means the other guy isn't there?
No, he's there, but it doesn't matter. I have the, I have
the right to say under these circumstances that, you know, that I'm
just, that we're splitting it.
But the guy isn't there, then does he have a right to
do whatever he wants?
Yeah, I mean, I mean, I don't know who, who hears him
make a declaration, but yes, he has a unilateral right in this
case. Okay, so if he says I'm operating for myself. Okay, so
then this would basically work in a case where it would be
like אינו יכול להציל, eino yachol lehatzil, okay? So in case of
אינו יכול להציל, eino yachol lehatzil, it's הפקר, hefker, okay? So he
basically says, but okay, so all this stuff is הפקר, hefker, and
he basically says I'm no longer seeing myself as a partner to
my friend regarding this,
with this property. It's all הפקר, hefker, the troops are coming and
going to take it. From here on in, it's every man for
himself. And in that case, if he goes ahead and he saves
it, he gets to keep it because, that means he's separating? He's
separating, not we split, it's confusing, it means we're splitting the partnership,
not we're splitting the money. Yeah, yeah. So since we're splitting the
partnership and I'm operating now on my own behalf and the stuff
is הפקר, hefker, now if I save it, I'm saving it all
for myself. לא אמר, lo amar, but if I don't say anything,
so even if the stuff is הפקר hefker because it's a normal
case of אינו יכול להציל, eino yachol lehatzil, but okay, but I'm
still operating as part of our partnership. And therefore לא פלי, lo
palli, I did not split the partnership, so since I'm operating, if
I don't say anything, the implicit point is I'm operating on behalf
of the two of us. Okay, so yes, the stuff is הפקר,
hefker, but if you don't say anything, then you're operating on behalf
of the two of us because the two of us were in
partnership. Alright, so that's one way. רבא אמר
הכא בפועלי עסקינן, Rava amar hacha b'po'alei maskinan, a similar approach. We're
talking about workers. So it's basically now, the idea that we split
לאמצע, l'emtza, that would be funny because it sounds like I actually
have a stake in this property. But the similar point is is
that I'm in your employ, I'm working here for Michael. Okay, if
I don't say anything, so again, it's going to get taken by
the troops, under normal circumstances it's not salvageable, it's considered הפקר, hefker,
but if I don't say anything, then anything I'm doing because I
was hired by Michael to come and to watch his gold as
we went through, as we took the caravan through the desert. So
if I don't say anything, then I'm acting on behalf of my
employer and I'm saving it for Michael's sake. Okay, but if I
do say something, I say I'm doing it for myself, it means
I can say, okay, I quit my job, I'm no longer working
for you, now I'm working for myself and I get to keep
it for myself.
He quits on the train line along the way.
Exactly. Okay, וכרבא דאמר רבא פועל יכול לחזור בו אפילו
בחצי היום, u'che'Rava d'amar Rava po'el yachol lachazor bo afilu b'chatzi hayom,
that a worker, one of the worker's rights we talked about the
other day, okay, a worker can quit his job even in the
middle of the day. You hired him for the day, it's not
indentured servitude, okay, he's allowed to quit even during the middle of
the day. וכמה דלא הדר ביה כרשותיה דבעל הבית, u'che'ma d'lo hadar
bei k'reshutei d'ba'al habayit,
but if I haven't quit my job yet, then if I don't
say anything, I'm still working for my employer. And therefore, if I'm
not saying anything and I just save it, I'm saving it for
my employer. If I do say I'm saving it for myself, it
means forget this job, every man for himself now. Okay, ובהאי הדר
ביה טעמא אחרינא הוא דכתיב. u'v'hai hadar bei ta'ama achrina hu d'chtiv.
Now, but when he does, sort of leave the reverse, not reverse,
whatever, reverse himself, meaning when he changes his mind, when he basically
quits his job, there's a reason you're allowed to quit your job
in the middle of the day. You're no longer working for your
employer. דכתיב, d'chtiv, the verse says, כי לי בני ישראל עבדים, ki
li b'nei yisrael avadim, the בני ישראל B'nei Yisrael are slaves to
Me. ולא עבדים לעבדים, v'lo avadim l'avadim, so everybody is a slave
here, you can't be a slave to a slave, right? Similar to
the obviously
negative rhetoric that the Gemara has or discussion the Gemara has against
somebody who sells himself into slavery even though it's limited slavery, it's
for six years. So here the idea is we don't want to
turn being an employee into being enslaved to your boss. So that's
a very powerful statement, right? Slave
to your job. I don't know what the, I am sure that
in different societies, I don't know what the reality was in the
time of the Gemara, like in Roman society. But no, I'm sorry,
you signed a contract, you're not allowed to leave in the middle
of the contract. And here חז"ל Chazal were very much, you can
leave, quit your job even in the middle of the day.
Okay, רב
אשי אמר כשיכול להציל על ידי
Rav Ashi amar keshe'yachol
lehatzil al yedei Yeah. Or is this just a regular, just oral
agreement?
You could come work
for me today and then you don't feel it in the middle
of the day? No, no, I see.
There could be penalty clauses. There could be consequences, but you're entitled
to quit. You can't force me to work. Okay. So the גמרא
Gemara says, רב אשי אמר כשיכול להציל ידי דחקה. Rav Ashi ammar
k'sheyachol lehatzil yadei dechaka. When you are, if the case is, is
that like we've been discussing before, that the stuff could be salvaged,
but only with effort. So in that case, so how does it
matter? It's still not הפקר. hefker. So גלי דעתיה לעצמו לא גלי
דעתיה לאמצע. galli da'atei l'atzmo, lo galli da'atei l'emtza. So if you
make it clear that, let me just, רש"י Rashi says, oh, so
רש"י Rashi says in this case, and that goes back to Michael,
where are the other where are the other owners of the of
the stuff. So in this case where it only could be salvaged
with effort, if I say I'm going to keep it to myself
and Michael here is a part owner, you know, also owns some
of the property, and he doesn't say, no you're not, buddy that's
my stuff, he just hears it and is quiet, that means that
he basically feels like, well what the heck, the stuff is lost
anyway. So he extent essentially hearing that and being quiet is accepting
it as loss and implicitly יאוש ye'ush and being מפקיר mafkir it.
Okay. But if he but if I don't say anything, then then
since it is it is potentially salvageable, we don't assume it's הפקר,
hefker, and therefore the owner still retains it. Okay. That is the
end of all those cases about something that's about to be lost,
its status of being הפקר hefker or not. Now we continue with
the next
משנה. mishnah. הגוזל שדה מחבירו ונטלוה מסיקין. ha-gozel sadeh me-chavero ve-netaluha masikin.
Back to גזילה. gezeilah. Okay, you basically went ahead and stole a
field from somebody else and of course the question is how exactly
do you steal a field, like you know you claim it for
yourself, you keep the other person off, you didn't physically take it
away, and to what degree do normal laws of גזילה gezeilah apply.
So this משנה mishnah initially starts by assuming that maybe it does
seem like normal laws of גזילה gezeilah apply. ונטלוה מסיקין, ve-netaluha masikin,
and some bandits take it, okay, away from you. Just you know
shows you, you know you steal somebody'll steal from you. אם מכת
מדינה היא, im makas medinah hi, if it basically is a case
where everybody in the you know in the county here, it's literally
country or whatever, anyway you know everybody in this area is having
their field seized by you know by bandits or whatever by you
know who knows troops, whatever invading armies, whatever the case might be.
So it's not you specifically this field, everybody's field. In that case,
אומר לו הרי שלך לפניך. omer lo harei shelach lefanecha. You say
to the owner, all right you know what, here's your field back.
Okay it's in the hand of these now troops. Okay. אם מחמת
הגזלן, im machamas ha-gazlan, however if it was before they
No they took it now. Yeah they took it already now. So
so you took it, you owe the owner, do you have to
replace it to the owner, or whatever, but now it's in the
hands of these invading troops that have now seized everybody's fields in
the in the region. So you can say look you know presumably
what you're really saying is that even if I had done nothing
your field would have been taken by them. So in the end
of the day I really didn't do anything to you, so we
treat it as if I did nothing.
Can you give me a case of a guy being held up
here's $20 oh there's bandits on like every street corner robbing everybody
is
that what No because this part of the question is is how
much is this part of the idea that קרקע karka is not
stolen. Okay. Which is the גמרא Gemara really the basic issue that's
in this משנה mishnah is not really explored by the גמרא. Gemara.
We're going to see in a minute the גמרא's Gemara going to
use it to take off to a very fascinating and different issue,
but not the real point of this משנה. mishnah. אם מחמת הגזלן
חייב להעמיד לו שדה אחר. im machamas ha-gazlan chayav l'amidi lo sadeh
acher. But if it was taken by these troops because of me,
because they basically you know have some eye on me, I owe
them money I whatever and they took it because of of me
because they perceived it to be mine or somehow they were attracted
to it because of me, and it's all my fault, then I
have to replace it. So the funny thing here is why exactly
first of all what's the difference whether I'm to blame or not
to blame. Usually אומר לו הרי שלך לפניך omer lo harei shelach
lefanecha is whether it's considered to be damaged or not. What difference
does that make. But there maybe you could say it's sort of
like if you remember before like the flip of a case like
you know if money is in you know is sort of discontinued,
is it discontinued everywhere, discontinued to be visible or not visible. So
here maybe it's like a little bit of the flip. If everybody's
field is being taken, so it's not like this is considered damage,
this is the reality for everybody. You know, if it's just this
field that's being taken then it is considered damage relative to everybody
else's. You could somehow make it about whether it's considered to be
the same field, considered damaged relative to other people's. But but bottom
line is that I thought fields weren't stolen, I thought קרקע karka
wasn't stolen. I just walk away, it doesn't taking your קרקע karka
doesn't come with any liability. And this משנה mishnah assumes to seem
like קרקע karka is stolen, but then what's the difference between these
two scenarios. So it's really not clear what's going on in the
משנה. mishnah. You could read it as a type of more of
a גרמי garmi type of a case which is sort of I'm
maybe I'm saying it because what's going to come up in the
גמרא Gemara as you'll see, that technically קרקע karka isn't stolen and
you just walk away, but למעשה l'ma'aseh if basically it's your fault
this this army seized it because of you and it's your fault
or whatever you know then we basically make you pay because it's
your you're to blame for the damage essentially that occurred. All right
so but it's not really clear what's going on in the משנה.
mishnah. Why is one case אומר לו הרי שלך לפניך omer lo
harei shelach lefanecha why is the other case not. Whatever happened to
the fact that you're really קרקע's karka not seen as נגזלת nigzeles
as able to be stolen as leading to liabilities.
So again the best I could say is that if you're to
blame and this person If you're to blame and this person now
doesn't have their field back because these troops are on because you
got involved, that's maybe some type of a גרמי garmi responsibility anyway,
and that's similar to where the גמרא Gemara is going to go,
and maybe that's why I'm saying it. Yeah.
So by your logic, if you stole my field, and the troops
are going, because not because of you, because of me, then you
could also say רישא כלפניך. reisha kol panecha.
Absolutely. Okay. אמר רב נחמן. Amar Rav Nachman. Anyway, let's see where
the גמרא Gemara goes with it. אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק מאן
דתני מציקין לא משתבש ומאן דתני מציקין לא משתבש. Amar Rav Nachman
bar Yitzchak man detani matzikin lo mishtabesh uman detani matzikin lo mishtabesh.
Whether your גירסא girsa is מציקין matzikin with a ש sin or
מציקין matzikin with a—what'd I say?—with a ס, samech, thank you, with
a צ, tzadi, either one is an acceptable text of this משנה.
Mishna. It's not a corrupt text. מאן דתני מציקין לא משתבש, Man
detani matzikin lo mishtabesh, go by the second one, מציקין matzikin with
a צ, tzadi, דכתיב במצור ובמצוק. dechsiv b'matzor uv'matzok. Right? There you
go. Right? In, you know, in siege and in siege, I don't
know whatever this is. Anyway,
but you're being besieged by troops, so מציקין matzikin are troops that
are besieging and seizing the property. מאן דתני מציקין לא משתבש דכתיב
ירש הצלצל? Man detani matzikin lo mishtabesh dechsiv yerash hatzlatzal? ייירש? Yiyarash?
No, that's what it said. ייירש הצלצל, Yiyarash hatzlatzal, that
the הצלצל hatzlatzal
will despoil your field. So what does that mean, despoil? So
מתרגמינן יחסניניה סקאה. metargemina yachsneineh saka'ah. What's סקאה? saka'ah? That's the word
מציקין. matzikin. So רש״י Rashi says the word סקאה saka'ah is a
type of a locust, okay? And therefore it means that, you know,
locusts, they cover the field and they just, you know, move in,
they're invasive, and they take stuff that isn't theirs, they eat up
all the grain. So therefore it's sort of making, you know, using
as a metaphor here, they're like locusts, and that's the word מציקין.
matzikin. תוספות Tosafot says the word סקאה saka'ah means like to rise
up and it really means like the enemy. It doesn't mean locust,
it's not a metaphor, it's more literal. Okay, or enemy, I understand,
but anyway, for specifically what the word means. Moving on. אם מחמת
הגזלן חייב. Im machmas hagazlan chayav. If it's the גזלן gazlan's fault
that it was taken, then he has to reimburse. היכי דמי? Heichi
dami? What does it mean it's his fault? אילימא דאנסוה לארעא דידיה
ולא אנסוה לכולה ארעא. Ilima d'ansuh l'ara dideh v'lo ansuh l'kulah ara.
If it's—if all it's saying is that these troops or whatever they
are seized just his land, the land of the גזלן gazlan including
the land he stole, and it didn't seize other people's lands. הא
מרישא שמעת מינה. Ha me'reisha shamas mina. That's implicit from the beginning
of the משנה. Mishna. אם מכת מדינה היא אומר הרי שלך לפניך.
Im makas medina hi omer harei shelcha l'fanecha. If it's occurring to
everybody, you walk away. So implicit in that is אם לאו, im
lav, if it's not happening to everybody, if it's just happening to
you, לא, lo, you don't walk away, you have to reimburse. So
why did you have to spell it out? And of course the
משנה Mishna often spells out both sides. But the way תוספות Tosafot
explains the question is why didn't the משנה Mishna just say אם
מכת מדינה היא אומר הרי שלך לפניך ואם לאו, im makas medina
hi omer harei shelcha l'fanecha v'im lav, you know,
he's חייב. chayav. Why does it say אם מחמת הגזלן? im machmas
hagazlan? Even that's not such a big question, it's just a parallel
phrasing, but obviously the גמרא Gemara is getting somewhere. So the גמרא
Gemara says לא צריכא דאחויי אחוויה. lo tzricha d'achvei achveih. And this
is going to be the focus of the whole דף, daf, where
the case is not just that bandits moved in and seized your
property, but basically it's not a case of גזילה gezeila at all.
Some bandits came up or troops or you know and and said
show us where ראובן Reuven's field is, we want to seize ראובן
Reuven's field. And me being a good citizen I point out where
ראובן Reuven's field is, and then they go and they seize ראובן
Reuven's field. So that's a different case, it's not about גזילה gezeila
at all. מחמת הגזלן, Machmas hagazlan, why it's called מחמת הגזלן, machmas
hagazlan, not clear, we'll see in a minute. But anyway, if I
basically point out the field and the field gets seized, I'm liable.
Very different scenario.
Assume that you're the only one that knew, like they couldn't have
found...
No, no, it doesn't matter if I'm the only one that knew,
I was the one who did it.
Okay, so דאחויי אחוויה d'achvei achveih means he told on.
Yeah, he showed, he pointed it out.
He pointed it out. Right.
Like this army is asking you where something is, you're going to—you're
supposed to risk your life?
Well, so that's what we're going to get to. We're going to
get to the question of whether you're אונס ones or not אונס.
ones. It's a big debate of the ראשונים. Rishonim. It's going to
come up in a minute. Okay, so we're going to see that.
ודאחויי אחוויה. V'd'achvei achveih.
So the גמרא Gemara says לישנא אחרינא, lishna achrina, another way of
saying this, הכא במאי עסקינן כגון דאנסוהו עכו״ם. hacha bamai askinan kegon
d'ansuhu akum. So the first one it wasn't forced that your life
was at stake, maybe the first one they were just asking you
for a favor. Okay, but here they hold a gun to your
head.
ואמרו ליה אחוי ארעך. V'amru leh achvei arach. Show us your land.
ואחוי ההיא בהדייהו. V'achvei hahi bahadeihu.
So he said oh here's all my land, so they seize your
land but you pointed out the one you stole among your land.
So then you know you shouldn't have pointed that one out, that
was that wasn't yours, that was something you stole. Okay, but the
bottom line is in both of these cases, and we have yet
to have a case where—it's never explicit yet, because you could have—you
didn't have to point out the stolen one as your land. The
first case it wasn't clear they were holding a gun to your
head. Right now all we have the idea is, we'll get to
the case about being really forced in a minute, but you're just
volunteering, you could have said I don't know, you pointed it out,
and therefore you're חייב chayav for the damage that's done. So the
question is what type of liability is this? And the גמרא Gemara
is going to say much later on, but תוספות Tosafot mentions, brings
it in here, it's a type of a גרמי, garmi, right? It's
you really just גרמא, grama, it's indirect. It's not considered גזילה, gezeila,
it's more considered מזיק. mazik. You have troops now that are staying
on your field, right, in a way the field isn't even damaged.
So anyway it's a type of a גרמי. garmi. But this is
now the big case of—now this is more broadly, I'm sure you've
all heard of the... concept of a מוסר, moser, right? Somebody who
hands over a Jew to the non-Jewish authorities. Here you're being מוסר
moser their land, and a little bit we're going to get to
the idea that if you start by being מוסר moser their land,
does it ultimately lead to them their lives also being in danger?
Once the government starts getting its claws, like once the mafia takes
a little bit of an interest into your business, you know, not
good for any- not good. So anyway, but here it seems to
be it's a type of a גרמי. garmi. You are the cause
of it, it directly happened as a result, you're liable. Now the
גמרא Gemara says: הכא במאי עסקינן.
hacha bemai askinan.
Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara says like this: ההוא גברא דאחוי אכרייא דחטי
דבי ריש גלותא. hahu gavra de-achvei achraye d'chite d'vei Reish Galuta. So
a certain guy pointed out a pile of wheat that belonged to
the ריש גלותא, Reish Galuta, which is you know the Jewish head
of the government, but they were biased by the non-Jewish authorities. Okay.
אתא לקמיה דרב נחמן, ata l'kamei d'Rav Nachman, came to רב נחמן.
Rav Nachman. רב נחמן Rav Nachman actually was related to the ריש
גלותא. Reish Galuta. חייביה רב נחמן לשלומי. chayveih Rav Nachman l'shlumei. רב
נחמן Rav Nachman said you gotta pay for that pile of wheat
that you handed over to the authorities from the that you know.
יתיב רב יוסף אחוריה דרב הונא בר חייא. yativ Rav Yosef achorei
d'Rav Huna bar Chiya. So רב יוסף Rav Yosef was sitting behind
רב הונא בר חייא. Rav Huna bar Chiya. ויתיב רב הונא בר
חייא קמיה דרב נחמן. v'yativ Rav Huna bar Chiya kamei d'Rav Nachman.
So as
רב נחמן Rav Nachman gave the ruling, then רב הונא בר חייא
Rav Huna bar Chiya and behind him רב יוסף. Rav Yosef. אמר
ליה רב הונא בר חייא לרב נחמן. amar lei Rav Huna bar
Chiya l'Rav Nachman. רב הונא בר חייא Rav Huna bar Chiya said
to רב נחמן: Rav Nachman: דינא או קנסא? dina o knasa? When
you're making this guy who pointed out the wheat pay, is that
like is that the law or is that a fine? אמר ליה
מתניתין היא. amar lei matnitin hi. He says, I don't know, it's
a משנה. Mishnah. He didn't say I don't know, anyway he says,
but דתנן אם מחמת הגזלן חייב להעמיד לו שדה. d'tnan im machamat
hagazlan chayav l'ha'amid lo sadeh. It says if the גזלן gazlan was
to blame you have to replace it. ואוקימנא דאחוי אחווייא, v'ukimna de-achvei
achvaya, and the tradition that we have to interpret what that משנה
Mishnah means is that the גזלן gazlan it's not really a גזלן,
gazlan, he just pointed out where the wheat was, where the field
was, and that creates liability. Okay. Now but- now but I don't
know whether it's a- whether דאורייתא d'Oraita or I'm not saying I
don't know, whatever, whether it's ממונא mamona or קנסא. knasa. בתר דנפיק,
batar denafik, after he left, אמר ליה רב יוסף לרב הונא בר
חייא. amar lei Rav Yosef l'Rav Huna bar Chiya. So רב יוסף
Rav Yosef was sitting two rows back, says to רב הונא בר
חייא: Rav Huna bar Chiya: מאי נפקא לך מינה? mai nafkâ lach
minâ? Why do you ask the question? What difference does it make
to you whether it's considered דין, din, like that's actually the you
know the law, or whether it's just a fine, אי דינא או
קנסא? ei dina o knasa? אמר ליה אי דינא גמרינן מינה. amar
lei ei dina gamrinan mina. Because if it's דין, din, then it's-
it represents a basic principle of law. And if it represents a
principle of law, we can apply it to all cases that follow
that same principle. אי קנסא, ei knasa, but if it's a fine,
then it's like an- then it's relatively arbitrary. There's no deeper principle
here, and maybe every circumstance is different, right? Maybe this guy was
a habitual person, maybe it was a certain time that it was
necessary to stamp down on this. There's a lot of circumstantial issues
that come up with whether we should impose fines. That's דאורייתא קנסא
d'Oraita knasa anyway, that's a different- I don't know the answer. Okay,
that's actually a תורה Torah קנס. knas. Anyway, but לא גמרינן מינה.
lo gamrinan mina. The point is anyway if it's a קנס knas
you cannot extrapolate.
Okay so you see you can't deduct a תורה Torah קנס? knas?
Yeah I mean for people or חרם cherem and all other like
extra-judicial thing. Anyway. ומנא תימרא דמקנסא לא גמרינן? umana teimra d'miknasa lo
gamrinan? And how do you know that from קנס knas you cannot
extrapolate? דתניא, detanya, it was taught in a ברייתא: braita: בראשונה היו
אומרים. barishona hayu omrim. Originally they would say המטמא והמנסך, hametamei v'hamenasech,
that if somebody makes somebody's grain טמא tamei or pours somebody's wine
to עבודה זרה, avoda zara, they have to pay for it. Now
the big point is is that זה היזק שאינו ניכר, zeh hezek
she'eino nikar, the damage is not visible. You can't see that the
that the grain is טמא tamei or the wine has been poured
to עבודה זרה. avoda zara. And even though non-visible damage you normally
should be exempt, they nevertheless said that you had to pay. Okay,
that's what they said originally.
I mean cause a whole barrel now is the problem because a
part you spilled is obvious you pay for it.
Yeah, or you could spill it from one into another but- yeah.
חזרו לומר אף המדמע. chazru lomar af hamedameia. Then they said, you
know what? Not only that case, even if you mixed up תרומה
terumah grain into חולין chulin grain. Because now the whole thing has
to be treated like תרומה terumah and has less of a market
value. Okay. חזרו chazru in, only they went back and they gave
a new ruling. לא חזרו לא, lo chazru lo, but if they
had not given a new ruling, you could not have extended it.
מאי טעמא, mai ta'ama, what's the reason? לאו משום דקנסא היא? lav
mishum d'knasa hi? It must be because this isn't the דין, din,
the דין din is היזק שאינו ניכר לאו שמיה היזק. hezek she'eino
nikar lav shemei hezek. It's not היזק. hezek. It's a fine. וקנסא
לא גמרינן מינה. v'knasa lo gamrinan mina. And we couldn't extrapolate. So
if they wanted to apply it to another case it needed another
ruling. So here you see something that is a fine you cannot
extrapolate to other cases. גמרא Gemara says: לא. lo. No, it's not
necessarily a fine. Maybe it was a דין, din, but there was
a logic why they thought that it might not extend to the
third case. Because even a דין din has parameters. מעיקרא סברי להפסד
מרובה חששו להפסד מועט לא חששו. me'ikara savri l'hefsed merubeh chashshu l'hefsed
muat lo chashshu. That they this would only apply to cases of
large loss, right? Because the המטמא והמנסך hametamei v'hamenasech were the whole
wine basically became unusable. As a small loss they weren't concerned. A
small loss was mixing it up with the תרומה terumah with the
other grain because it's not- because it's just now has a תרומה
terumah status, but you don't have to basically throw it out. ולבסוף
סברי להפסד מועט נמי חששו. u'levasof savri l'hefsed muat nami chashshu. In
the end they figured you know what we're going to apply it
even to cases of small loss. Now the funny thing is saying
it's a concern of degree of loss does not seem to me
to be a consideration of דין, din, right? It seems to me
to be consideration of policy, right? I mean if this type of
an act has liability it shouldn't matter big loss or small loss.
To say it'll only apply in cases of big loss and not
small is a policy consideration which to me seems to suggest קנס.
knas. So it seems interesting that the גמרא Gemara has an idea
that there's a concept of
דין. din. but we're going to extend rabbinically the definition of היזק.
hezek. And the way we're extending it is by taking into certain
under certain circumstances taking into policy considerations but we're still conceptualizing it
as a type of a היזק hezek and we're not conceptualizing it
as a fine. You see my point here? Meaning normally policy leads
to קנס. knas. Policy doesn't lead to דין. din. Okay, so part
of this issue is not just what motivates us to be doing
this, you know, maybe we're motivated due to policy concerns and people
are getting out of hand, but in the end of the day
how do we frame it? Do we frame it as now an
expansion of the הלכה halakha or do we frame it as a
sign that we're imposing on someone? Okay, so anyway it says you
can't learn from here because it could be דין din but there's
still a logic to distinguish between the cases. So the גמרא Gemara
says one minute. והתני אבוה דרבי אבין Ve-tani Abuha de-Rabbi Avin but
the father of רבי אבין Rabbi Avin teaches a ברייתא baraita a
different way. בראשונה היו אומרים המטמא והמדמע Be-reshona hayu omrim ha-metame ve-ha-medamea
first they only applied it to the case of making the grain
טמא tamei or mixing it up. חזרו לומר אף המנסך Chazru lomar
af ha-menasech then they said even pouring it to עבודה זרה. avodah
zarah. Now that the second case is a bigger הפסד. hefsed. Okay,
the wine is worthless. So so why didn't they just logically extrapolate?
So חזרו אין chazru in only when they went back and legislated
again. לא חזרו לא lo chazru lo otherwise not. מאי טעמא Mai
ta'ama what's the reason? לאו משום ד Lav mishum de obviously logically
that case certainly should have logically been included. לאו משום דלא גמרינן
מקנסא Lav mishum delo gamrinan mi-knasa must because we're seeing this as
a fine and even though logically other cases should be included, you
can't extrapolate if it's based on a concept of fine. So the
גמרא Gemara says no no it's not why it is. מעיקרא סבר
כרבי אבין ולא סבר כרבי ירמיה Me'ikara savar ke-Rabbi Avin velo savar
ke-Rabbi Yirmiyah no it's based on דין din and even based on
דין din there would have been a reason to exclude the case
of wine, of pouring the wine to עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. Why?
It's the debate of רבי אבין Rabbi Avin and רבי ירמיה. Rabbi
Yirmiyah. מעיקרא סבר כרבי אבין Me'ikara savar ke-Rabbi Avin originally they thought
wine you would not have to pay by pouring to עבודה זרה
avodah zarah like רבי אבין. Rabbi Avin. דאמר רבי אבין De-amar Rabbi
Avin זרק חץ מתחלה עד סוף ארבע וקרע שירים בהליכתו zarak chetz
mit-chilah ad sof arba ve-karah shirayim be-halichato somebody on שבת Shabbos shot
an arrow and you're considered carrying when it goes four amos in
רשות הרבים. reshus ha-rabim. Okay, so you shot the arrow and at
a two אמה amma marker it tore through somebody's nice shirt and
then it landed four at the end of the four amos. Do
you say קים ליה בדרבה מיניה kam leh bi-derabbah minei that you're
doing an act that's liable to for the death penalty, חלול שבת
chillul Shabbos in the process of the act something is being damaged
you're exempt. Do you consider this to be while the act is
being done or is the act of חלול שבת chillul Shabbos only
taking place when the arrow rests and in the pathway it's not
yet the act of חלול שבת? chillul Shabbos? Okay, so originally...
originally he held in accord with...
originally he held in accord with... Yes, but is the but does
קים ליה kim leh apply to any part of the process or
does קים ליה kim leh only apply to the moment when you're
חייב? chayav? Okay, so פטור. patur. So he says you're exempt.
שהרי עקירה צורך הנחה she-harei akirah tzorech hanachah the picking up the
you know the whole act of חלול שבת chillul Shabbos requires all
these components. It needs to be picked up, it needs to be
put down four amos later and it needs to travel four amos.
So therefore all of this is part of the act of חלול
שבת chillul Shabbos and we say קים ליה kim leh and you're
exempt and that's why they originally said you're exempt for the pouring
of the wine because you're doing it in an act that's חייב
מיתה chayav misah in an act of עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. Okay,
ומתחייב בנפשו u-mitchayev benafsho
and you're liable. ולבסוף סבר U-le-basof savar in the end he held
כרבי ירמיה ke-Rabbi Yirmiyah like רבי ירמיה. Rabbi Yirmiyah. דאמר רבי ירמיה
De-amar Rabbi Yirmiyah משעת הגבהה קנייה mishas hagbahah kanyei יתחייב ליה ממון
yitchayev leh mamon מתחייב בנפשו לא הוי עד שעת ניסוך. mitchayev benafsho
lo havah ad she'as nisuch.
So רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmiyah says specifically about the case of יין
נסך yayin nesech that it's not the same. Why is it not
the same? Because he said he said or not the same he
basically disagrees. Anyway he said when you pick up the wine you're
חייב chayav for גניבה gnevah and you're not חייב chayav for עבודה
זרה avodah zarah until you pour it. Okay, so he act now
one way to read that is he would argue on the שבת
Shabbos case as well and he would say I don't care if
it's during the process of the act. We only say קים ליה
kim leh at the moment of liability. So the moment of liability
by the arrow is at the end and only then would we
say קים ליה kim leh not during the process. And the moment
of liability by pouring the wine is when the wine is poured,
not on but the act of גניבה gnevah you know of course
you could say is it גניבה gnevah or is it מזיק? mazik?
The act of גניבה gnevah came when the wine was picked up.
Okay, so therefore that's why I mean this is a very whole
interesting סוגיה sugya and we don't have really time to unpack that.
But the point is it could be debated whether you say קים
ליה kim leh in this case and therefore that was the issue.
So it is דין, din, it's not it doesn't matter whether it's
דין din or whether it's קנס. knas. Oh now I realized what
I was saying it wrong. I apologize. I apologize. Okay, the reason
is I mentioned before that because of the policy considerations it was
sounding like it was קנס. knas. It is assuming it's קנס. knas.
גמרא Gemara assumes it's not a question whether whether this payment here
about the מטמא מדמע metame medamea is דין din or קנס. knas.
Clearly it's קנס. knas. The דין din is היזק שאינו ניכר לא
שמיה היזק. hezek she'eino nikar lo shemeh hezek. You should not be
paid. Clearly any payment here is קנסא knasa and as a... Okay,
the question is, can you extrapolate from one ruling of קנס Knas
and extend it to other logically similar ones? Okay, so the answer
is you see if they needed another ruling you can’t extrapolate. And
the גמרא Gemara says no, you can extrapolate, but only in ones
that are logically similar. Okay, so the case before so initially the
question was, a case of lesser loss isn’t logically similar. So even
if you’re allowed to extrapolate by קנס, Knas, they couldn’t extrapolate to
include the case of lesser loss. Here they’re saying even if it’s
קנס Knas and you can extrapolate, it wouldn’t necessarily apply to a
case of קים ליה, Kim lei, okay, and this might have been
constituted a קים ליה Kim lei and that was the question whether
whether this was a case of קים ליה Kim lei or not.
All right, so anyway this is all a bit of a digression,
but it gets us to the question of when you’re saying you
have to pay for pointing out that field, this is an important
question. Is that seen as a קנס Knas and a way of
stamping down on, you know, behavior that’s obviously is injurious to society,
or is it seen as a type of a דין Din that
you brought about damage to something else, that’s like a גרמי? Garmi?
By the way, that’s a whole debate in the ראשונים Rishonim about
גרמי Garmi in general, right, when you burn somebody’s שטרות, Shtaros, other
cases of גרמי. Garmi. You put poison in front of somebody’s animal
or whatever the case might be, right, is it a קנס Knas
as a way of punishing and stopping the behavior, or is it
a type of דין? Din? Is it an expansion of what it
means to damage somebody’s property? Okay, so that’s the question here, and
the logical question is if it’s קנס Knas you might not be
able to extrapolate. The case of קנס Knas was היזק שאינו ניכר,
Hezek she’eino nikar, and the גמרא Gemara says no, maybe you can
extrapolate, but you have to extrapolate within logical parameters and some of
those would not have been normal extensions of the same case. Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara continues.
Okay,
רב הונא בר יהודה Rav Huna bar Yehuda איקלע לבי אביוני. ikla
l’vei Avyonei. So רב הונא בר יהודה Rav Huna bar Yehuda came
to this place of the house of אביוני. Avyonei. אתא לקמיה דרבא.
Asa l’kamei d’Rava. Yeah, אביוני Avyonei is a usually right right. אתא
לקמיה דרבא, Asa l’kamei d’Rava, he came to רבא. Rava. אמר ליה,
Amar lei, כלום מעשה בא לידך? Klum ma’aseh ba l’yadcha? Hey,
how you doing there רבא, Rava, have any interesting things happened to
you this last week? אמר ליה, Amar lei, yeah, you know what?
ישראל שאנסוהו עובדי כוכבים להראות ממון חבירו בא לידי. Yisrael she’ansuho ovdei
kochavim l’haros mamon chaveiro ba l’yadi. I had a case where a
Jew was forced, and here we have the case right about that
explicitly being forced, and pointed out property of a non-Jew and וחייבתי
v’hiyavti and I made him reimburse. אמר ליה, Amar lei, so he
said to, so he said to רבא, Rava, הדר עובדא למר. Hadar
ovda l’mar. You know what? You should go ahead and reverse your
ruling and give the money back to the guy who pointed out.
Why? דתניא, D’tanya, we taught in a ברייתא, Braisa, ישראל שאנסוהו עובדי
כוכבים להראות ממון חבירו פטור. Yisrael she’ansuho ovdei kochavim l’haros mamon chaveiro
patur. If a Jew was forced by non-Jews and he pointed out
his friend’s money, he’s exempt. ואם נטל ונתן ביד
חייב. V’im natal v’nasan b’yad chayav. Only if he literally picks it
up and hands it over is he חייב. chayav. Now, there’s a
very interesting debate in the ראשונים, Rishonim, what is the difference of
pointing out and handing over? So רש"י Rashi says the basic difference
is that handing over you’re doing more than is asked of you.
And therefore you’re not forced to hand it over. You could have
just said where it is and you said, 'oh, let me help
you' and you went and you picked it up and you delivered
it. Okay? And that makes you because in that act of delivering
it nobody was holding a gun to your head, all you had
to do was point and you now actively took it without being
forced to take it, so then you’re a גנב, ganav, you’re a
מזיק. mazik. All right, so that would mean if they would actually
hold a gun to your head and make you hand it over
you would be exempt. Other ראשונים, Rishonim, the רי"ף Rif and others,
say the גמרא Gemara should have then just distinguished between whether you
were forced in that moment or not forced, right? It’s not really
about handing it. And they say even with a gun to your
head, okay, you actually are liable, which is a very strange point.
Like what are you supposed to do? You’re not supposed to give
up your life. You might remember by the way a while ago
we learned a discussion about whether מותר לאדם להציל עצמו בממון של
חבירו? Mutar l’adam l’hatzil atzmo b’mamon shel chaveiro? Are you allowed to
save yourself? Now, it is very strange to think you have to
give up your life rather than cause damage to your friend’s property.
So most ראשונים Rishonim understand the question is fine, you’re allowed to
do it, but you still have to pay for it. Okay? So
yes, you’re allowed, nobody is going to make you up in heaven
say how could you do a sin of גזילה? gezeilah? Of course,
you know, your life was at stake, nobody is going to blame
you morally for doing it, but nevertheless, your friend’s property was destroyed.
Why should your friend have to be the one that paid? He
lost his property in the process of you saving your life, you
should be the one to be reimbursing him for that. Okay, still
with all of that being said, it is a little bit strange
if the gun is being held to your head. It’s one thing
to say I don’t know like you know somebody is running after
me and I take Michael’s, you know, whatever I take, I take
his iPhone and I throw it at the guy to distract him
so I run away. So then okay, I broke his iPhone in
saving my life, I should reimburse him for his iPhone. Okay here,
the guy holds the gun to my head and says show me
where Michael’s iPhone is or hand me over Michael’s iPhone, I pick
it up and how much am I really doing that, right? How
much, there the whole act is compelled and it shouldn’t even be
attributed to me and seen as my act. So that is a
little bit different,
nevertheless that is how a number of ראשונים Rishonim read it. If
I actively do it, even if a gun is held to my
head, nobody is blaming me for it, of course it's what I
was supposed to do, but I have to reimburse. Yes, Jenna?
I feel like the difference between the iPhone example and the land
example is that like someone's coming after you and you use whatever's
in the area that happens to save your life, you're the one
in trouble, right? Whereas the land one, this army is clearly going
after Michael, right? It's not about you, you're like collateral.
That's even a better point. That's, I mean, this is strengthening my
point that with the gun to your head, you're just sort of
being used by them. You're really not even an agent in that.
Right.
I wonder if it's different if you're the one handing it over
somehow.
Like even if they were telling me to hand it over?
Yeah, that like somehow you're more involved in the land in that
way. Like if they're just asking you to point it out, okay,
you say no, they're going to ask the next person, like it's
not about you.
Right, it makes you more, but again, all of that could be
as if I choose to hand it over, right? With the gun
to your head, and what you add strengthens it, right? Not only
am I being used by them without being an agent here, right,
my agency doesn't exist really in this case, but your point is
right, they're anyway not interested in me, they're interested in the land.
So to say רש"י's Rashi reading, that I didn't have to hand
it over, I could have just pointed it out, is a better,
makes more logical sense. But many ראשונים Rishonim read this to mean
even with the gun to my head, I have to reimburse.
So I don't understand how the parallel is for the land because
for מטלטלין Metaltelin I pick it up...
No, we're no longer talking specifically about land. It says נתפו ונתנו
ביד. Natfo Venatno Beyad. We're not talking about land.
זהו ממון חבירו. Zeh Mamon Chaveiro.
ממון חבירו. Mamon Chaveiro.
Right. So then what do you... but land is no נתפו ונתנו
ביד. Natfo Venatno Beyad. Right. Okay, so then is it more לקולא
Lekula or more לחומרא? Lechumra?
It would be more לקולא Lekula then with the gun to your
head you'd always be exempt because you could never actually physically hand
it over. Right. Well, no, just her case wasn't limited to land.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay.
האנס שאנסו עובד כוכבים ואחוי ואחוי וחייב. Ha'anas She'ansu Oved Kochavim Ve'achvei
Ve'achvei Vechayav. אמר רבא אם הראה מעצמו כנתפו ונתנו ביד דמי. Amar
Rava Im Herah Me'atzmo Kenatfo Venatno Beyad Dami. If you volunteer the
information by pointing it out, then it's like you handed, then it's
like you handed it over. Great. So again, that raises the question
though, is the handing over because you didn't have to hand it
over or not? But certainly, if you did it on yourself, then
you have an agency, you weren't compelled, that's an obvious case you
should be חייב. Chayav. ההוא גברא דאנסוהו עובדי כוכבים ואחוי אחמרא דרב
מרי בריה דרב פנחס בריה דרב חסדא. Hahu Gavra De'ansuhu Ovdei Kochavim
Ve'achvei Achamra DeRav Mari Brei DeRav Pinchas Brei DeRav Chisda.
So a certain person was forced by the non-Jews and he pointed
out the wine of רב מרי, Rav Mari, etc., the son of
רב חסדא. Rav Chisda. אמר להו. Amar Lehu. Okay, and then the
question was, is he now going to have to reimburse? So אמר
להו דרו ואמטו בהדן. Amar Lehu Doru Ve'amtu Behadan. Come with us
and let's, you know, load yourself up, let's go on a journey,
let's go to court and see whether you have to reimburse or
not. דרו ואמטו בהדייהו. Doru Ve'amtu Behadeihu. He went with them, אתו
לקמיה דרב אשי, Atu Lekamei DeRav Ashi, came to רב אשי. Rav
Ashi. פטריה. Patrei. רב אשי Rav Ashi said you're exempt, you don't
have to reimburse. אמרו ליה רבנן לרב אשי והתניא נתפו ונתנו ביד
חייב. Amru Lei Rabanan LeRav Ashi Vehatanya Natfo Venatno Beyad Chayav. One
minute, didn't we say if you hand over with your hand, you're
חייב? Chayav? Now, of course it didn't say there that he handed
over, it just said אחוי, Achvei, he pointed it out, but anyway,
presumably it sounds like the case was he picked it up and
handed it over. אמר להו הני מילי דלא אוקמה עילויה מעיקרא. Amar
Lehu Hanei Milei Dela Okmei Ileiyei Me'ikara. That is if they're not
directly standing over the property they're trying to seize. אבל הכא דאוקמה
עילויה מעיקרא. Aval Hacha De'okmei Ileiyei Me'ikara. He originally got, you know,
he pointed it out. So they went, so they said show us
where the wine is. So he pointed it out, he said and
he showed them where it was. Okay. And there he was in
the cellar with all the wine. And they said great, now load
up our truck with it. Okay. So first, since they were already
there, okay, in that case מקליי קליי. Miklei Kalyai. It's like it's
burnt up. As soon as the troops are in his cellar, okay,
with the wine that he pointed out, and he then has to
physically hand it over at this stage, the wine is considered to
already be destroyed. So now actively participating is no longer destroying his
property. His property was already destroyed and that happened before he actively
participated. All right, so that's an interesting sort of loophole, as it
were. All right, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
איתיביה רבי אבהו לרב אשי. Eitivei Rabbi Abbahu LeRav Ashi. So רבי
אבהו Rabbi Abbahu asked רב אשי. Rav Ashi. אמר לו אנס, Amar
Lo Anas, so a, you know, a not
a
whatever, like
you know, a murderer,
a bandit says, הושיט לי פקיע עמיר זה, Hoshit Li Paki Amir
Zeh, hand me over this bundle of, of what, of grain or
something, אשכול ענבים זה, Eshkol Anavim Zeh, or this cluster of
grapes, והושיט לו. Vehoshit Lo. So you're חייב *chayav* and it sounds
like he's standing right there. So why are you חייב *chayav*? It's
נטל ונתן ביד *natal v'natan b'yad*, but you just said if you're
standing right there, it's like the thing is already destroyed. So the
גמרא *Gemara* says הכא במאי עסקינן כגון דקאי אעברא דנהרא *hacha b'mai
askinan kegon d'ka'ei a'avra d'nahara*. No, you're at two opposite sides of
the river. So actually he's not able to take it himself. Okay,
in that case that he's not able to take it himself, then
you are actively, you know, giving it and you're an active participant.
דיקא נמי דקתני הושיט *Dika nami d'katani hoshit*. It says, it says
extend to me this, ולא תני תן *v'lo tani ten*, not just
give it to me. שמע מינה *Shma mina*. So now, although the
גמרא *Gemara* again makes the distinction of if he's there or not
to whether the object is considered destroyed, it also helps us understand
a little bit why you're considered more of an agent even though
your life is being threatened. It's true your life is being threatened,
but you're still now, the גנב *ganav* is not right directly over
the object. You know, you're still bringing the object to the guy.
And it's true that he's threatening that if you don't do it
he'll kill you, but you're still the one that sort of is,
you know, there's a certain some greater degree here of making it
happen, you know, not totally directly being used by the guy, but
exerting, you know, myself sort of, there's some greater sense of agency.
So some way of understanding a little more. Okay, so now the
גמרא *Gemara* says like this. ההוא שוטא דהוו מנצו עליה בי תרי
*Hahu shuta d'havu mintsu alei bei trei*. So there was a certain,
what's a שוטא *shuta* again here? רש״י *Rashi* says, hold on,
oh, right, a net, a fishnet that was being, that was being
debated, fought over by two people. האי אמר דידי הוא והאי אמר
דידי הוא *Hai amar didi hu v'hai amar didi hu*. This one
says it's mine, this one says it's mine. אזל חד מינייהו ומסרה
לפרהגנא דמלכא *Azal chad mineihu u'masrah l'parhagna d'malka*. So one of them
just basically handed it over to the king's officer, you know, said,
well, since we're fighting it and I'm never going to get it,
sort of like King שלמה *Shlomo* he's doing to himself, might as
well just give it up, give it to the king. Okay. אמר
אביי *Amar Abaye*, no distractions. יכול לומר אנא כי מטי דידי מטי
*Yachol lomar ana ki mati didi mati*. So then the other guy
said, okay, you were a מוסר *moser*, pay me for my net.
So he says he could say, listen, it was my net I
gave away, I didn't go over your net. אמר ליה amar lei,
רבא וכל כי האי גוונא *Amar lei Rava v'chol ki hai gavna*?
Why would he be believed? He's claiming it, but they should have
to first try to prove whose net it was. He can't just
say it was my net and walk away. Okay, so אלא אמר
רבא משמתינן ליה עד דמייתי ליה וקאי בדינא *Ella amar Rava meshamtinan
lei ad d'maiti lei v'ka'ei b'dina*. We put, we put him in
חרם *cherem* until he retrieves the net and then we're able to
have the court case over the net. So he has to restore
it because of the possibility that it belongs to the other person
until we can sort of, so that we can work out that
case. Okay. ההוא גברא דהוה בעי אחוויי אתיבנא דחבריה *Hahu gavra d'hava
ba'ei achvuyei ativna d'chavrei*. Now we get to a really interesting story.
A certain man was prepared to point out אתיבנא דחבריה *ativna d'chavrei*,
his friend's straw, a thing that's relatively trivial, it's just straw anyway.
אתא לקמיה דרב *Ata l'kamei d'Rav*. So he came to רב Rav
*Rav*. Now, whether he came to רב Rav *Rav* to ask if
he's allowed to do it, the friend took him to רב Rav
*Rav*, it's interesting anyway. אמר ליה amar lei לא תחוי ולא תחוי
*Amar lei lo tachvei v'lo tachvei*. You better not, don't point it
out, don't point it out. אמר ליה amar lei, מחוינא ומחוינא *Amar
lei machvina u'machvina*. I don't care, I'm pointing it out, I'm going
to do that to protect my life or whatever I'm doing it.
Okay, so יתיב רב כהנא Rav Kahana קמיה דרב *Yativ Rav Kahana
kamei d'Rav*. So רב כהנא Rav Kahana *Rav Kahana* was sitting in
front of רב Rav. *Rav*. שמטיה לקועיה מיניה *Shamteih l'kueih mineih*. He
broke the guy's neck. He wanted to prevent this guy from doing
it. Now, he killed him, so much for life, it wasn't clear
in this case sort of that the guy's life was being threatened
or not, right, because until now we might make you pay, but
it doesn't seem like, you know, you have to, whatever. Who broke
the guy's neck? רב כהנא Rav Kahana
*Rav Kahana* broke the neck of the guy who was about to
be מוסר *moser*.
Okay, so קרי רב עילויה *Kari Rav ileih*.
So רב *Rav* said, בניך עולפו שכבו בראש כל חוצות כתוא מכמר
*Banecha ulpu shakvu b'rosh kol chutzot k'to michmar*. Your children have, you
know, have fainted and lied down, you know, in the, you know,
you know, in the outdoors like a
trapped bull or something. מה תוא זה כיון שנפל במכמר אין מרחמין
עליו *Mah to ze kivan shenafal b'michmar ein merachmin alav*. The same
way when the bull falls in a trap they have no compassion,
they slaughter it. אף ממון של ישראל כיון שנפל ביד עובדי כוכבים
*Af mamon shel Yisrael kivan shenafal b'yad ovdei kochavim*. The money of
the Jews, once the non-Jews start seizing and getting involved, you know,
start putting their eye on you, אין מרחמין עליו *ein merachmin alav*,
they have no compassion. Now who do they not have compassion on?
רש״י *Rashi* says it means then eventually the Jew's life will be
at stake, which makes sense why he was sort of seeing this
guy as a type of a רודף *rodef*. תוספות *Tosafot* says the
guy's property they'll have no compassion on, which doesn't explain it, okay,
but then why could you kill this guy?
You can't kill him then according to תוספות *Tosafot*.
No, because we're gonna, well, maybe, that's interesting, but that doesn't sound
like that. Then it sounds like the פסוק *pasuk* is being quoted
to somehow defend the action. Anyway, let's take a look where the
story goes. Okay, so I think you have to assume that the
guy's life was being threatened, that he was somehow seen as some
evil person that had to be stopped, right? I mean, if he
was coming to רב *Rav*, presumably he had a choice whether to
do it or not, right? Okay, so it sounds like there was
a case that maybe his property was being threatened, but it sounds
like he had a choice. Okay, and if he had a choice,
and therefore you can't, you know, to do it would be a
terrible thing, such a terrible thing it's not just a monetary issue,
that you know, רב כהנא Rav Kahana *Rav Kahana* felt he had
to take his life. So let's take a look.
אמר ליה Amar leh, רב *Amar lei Rav*...
Only רב, yeah. So רב said to him, כהנא, Kahana, כהנא, Kahana,
עד אידנא הוו פרסאי דלא קפדי אשפיכות דמים. Ad idna havu Parsai
d'lo kafdei ashfikhus damin. Until now we were only being ruled by
Persians. Persians don't care about murder. You could have gotten away with
it. והשתא יונאי דקפדי אשפיכות דמים, V'hashta Yavnai d'kafdei ashfikhus damin, and
now they are Greeks that are concerned about murder and you're not
going to get away with it. Now, of course, question is, is
the history right? Did the Greeks come after the Persians or before?
Which one really was? So if you look at the side, the
side has גרסא girsah that's the exact flip. So your English has
the Greeks,
yeah, the Greeks came after, but I mean historically the Greeks came
after, right?
The Greeks came after the Persians when the Jews were in
בבל?
Bavel? I'm sorry.
Yeah, so anyway,
so anyway, so there's a question which the order was and there's
also a question who
שיבת ציון Shivat Tzion was Persian or שיבת ציון Shivat Tzion was
Persian, right, right,
and afterwards what Hellenists?
Yeah, but the Hellenists in, but in where the Jews were, in
בבל, Bavel, they were when were there Hellenists in בבל? Bavel? I
don't know.
Anyway, what's the point though? What does it matter whether he's going
to get away with the murder?
Well, because we're going to see he's going to have to go
in hide if he's not going to get away with the murder.
If they actually were worried about it then he shouldn't have done
this anyway, meaning if the Greeks are מקפיד makpid on
murder then presumably you didn't have to kill this guy because they're
not going to kill you for. Oh, no, that's not what it
meant. No, no, that's not what it meant. Okay, what's past is
past. Now the question is, is there going to be repercussions? They're
going to find out you murdered this guy and you're going now
you better run.
No, no, what I'm saying is then if they actually are מקפיד
makpid on murder then presumably you didn't have to kill this guy
because they're not going to kill you for.
Oh, no, that's not what it meant. No, no, that's not what
it meant.
Okay, and Alexander of בבל, Bavel, that was
around the third century BC or something? Right, right. It was Persians
before that, the Persian Empire
in Israel, but
he took over all the lands of Alexander took over the whole
known world.
Yeah, I don't know how it affects.
Okay, so you're saying that when the Jews were in בבל Bavel
in the time of,
I don't know, this is late right, I mean these רבנים rabbanim
at the time of the Sassanid, anyway, I don't know enough the
history. Anyway, there's a question which is what the order was and
which one cared about Jews murdering other Jews. But right now we're
dealing with a government that cares about Jews murdering other Jews and
so you'd be so you're in trouble. Okay, ואמרי v'amri and they
say
what? What'd you say?
An index from Koren?
Yeah, one second, I just got to read this next line, ואמרי
v'amri and they say, מרדין מרדין, mardin mardin, which I would like
to read as murder murder. I don't know if that's exactly what
they say. They translate it as murder murder. So anyway they'll say
you're a murderer. So in that case קום סק לארץ ישראל, kum
sa'ak l'Eretz Yisrael, go run to Israel, so go hide from the
authorities, וקבל עלך דלא תקשי ליה לרבי יוחנן שבע שנין. v'kabel alach
d'lo tiklei l'Rabbi Yochanan sheva shanim. So of course you're going to
go to ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, you're going to want to go
to the ישיבה. yeshiva. The ישיבה yeshiva you're going to want to
go to is רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. So accept upon yourself that
you don't challenge him for seven years. Now why is that? It's
not clear. Like did you know, is that to not be discovered
by the authorities? Is that because even though you killed this guy
and it could be defendable, defensible, you really shouldn't have killed him?
So it's a type of גלות galus and an עונש onesh that
you're imposing on yourself. Never really spelled out why he's not supposed
to ask for seven years. What does Koren say about Greeks?
During רב's lifetime, after many generations of the empire being ruled by
the Parthians, the Persian Empire underwent a fundamental change and the Sassanid
emperors from central Persia came to power. Although the Parthians were also
Persian, they had been culturally more influenced by the Greeks who had
preceded them in the region of their empire than the Sassanids were.
Aha, so originally it was the Hellenized Persians, came after the Hellenized
Persians.
Right, so originally it was the Hellenized Persians, and then it's the
non-Hellenized Persian, right, and then it's the Persians that are more so
and the Hellenized Persians didn't care as much about Jews murdering other
Jews as the real Persians did.
Because it was a form of feudalism in which the central government
exhibited loose control, allowing a high degree of autonomy both for provincial
leaders, often called kings, and for different ethnic and religious groups.
Ah, so since it was an internal Jewish thing, so originally it
was the Hellenized Persian and it was more internal Jewish and you
could get away with it. Now we've got internal... very nice, okay,
so all right, good use of the card there. Okay, now let's
get let's read a little bit of this great story. Okay, אזל
אשכחיה לריש לקיש, azal ashchei l'Reish Lakish, so כהנא, Kahana, רב כהנא
Rav Kahana went to ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and
he found ריש לקיש Reish Lakish דיתיב ומסיים מסיבתא דיומא לרבנן, d'yativ
u'mesayem mesivta d'yoma l'rabbanan, and he was finishing the חזרה שיעור chazarah
shiur for the rabbis. ריש לקיש Reish Lakish was רבי יוחנן's Rabbi
Yochanan prime תלמיד talmud and colleague and he was reviewing the lesson
for all the other רבנים rabbanim of the
academy. אמר להו amar lehu ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, אמר להו amar
lehu so רב כהנא Rav Kahana... said to the other רבנים, rabbanim,
ריש לקיש היכא, Reish Lakish heicha, where is ריש לקיש? Reish Lakish?
אמר ליה, Amar leh, אמר ליה Amar leh, they said to him,
אמאי amai why do you want to know? אמר ליה, Amar leh,
האי קושיא והאי קושיא hai kushya v'hai kushya because I have this
קושיא kushya and this קושיא. kushya. והאי פירקא והאי פירקא v'hai pirka
v'hai pirka and then I have this answer and this answer. So
like he, you know, he was showing how smart whatever, like you
know all the problems he had and all the answers, right? אמרו
ליה לריש לקיש, amru lei l'Reish Lakish, they said to ריש לקיש
Reish Lakish there's a guy that came from בבל Bavel and he's
asking all these קושיות kashyas on the שיעור, shiur, on
the you know what you told over in the name of
רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. אזל ריש לקיש אמר ליה לרבי יוחנן, azal
Reish Lakish amar lei l'Rabbi Yochanan, ריש לקיש Reish Lakish went and
told רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, ארי עלה מבבל. ari ala mi-Bavel. Bavel.
A lion came up from
בבל Bavel. *Bavel*. Lion מחר במתיבתא *machar bi-metivta*, go and look into
the סוגיא *sugya* you're going to teach tomorrow
because he's going to challenge you a lot or whatever, you know,
he really you got- you got some new student here. Okay. למחר
L'machar אותביה בדרא קמא *Le-machar otvei be-dara kama*. The next day, they
put רב כהנא Rav Kahana *Rav Kahana* in the first row of
the בית מדרש *Beis Medrash*, right for the prize students. Now קמיה
דרבי יוחנן *kamei de-Rabbi Yochanan* in front of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
*Rabbi Yochanan*. Now remember, he had accepted upon himself to not challenge
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan. *Rabbi Yochanan* for seven years. אמר שמעתתא *Amar
shmaitata*, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan. *Rabbi Yochanan* taught some סוגיא *sugya* ולא
אקשיה *ve-lo akshyei*, and he was silent. He didn't ask. שמעתתא ולא
אקשיה *Shmaitata ve-lo akshyei*, another teaching and he was silent. אחתוהו אחורי
שבע דרי *Achatvei achorei sheva darei*. So they put him to the
back of the class, okay, seven- seven rows in the back. עד
דאותביה בדרא בתרא *Ad de-otvei be-dara batra* until they put him at
the very back row. אמר ליה רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan לריש לקיש
*Amar lei Rabbi Yochanan le-Reish Lakish*, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan *Rabbi Yochanan*
said to ריש לקיש *Reish Lakish*, ארי שאמרת *Ari she-amarta*, the lion
you were talking about נעשה שועל *na'asa shual*, it turns out to
be a fox. So רב כהנא Rav Kahana *Rav Kahana* heard this,
was very offended. He said, יהא רעוא *yehei ra'ava*, may it be
God's will דהני שבע דרי *de-hanei
sheva darei*, the seven rows that I was put back ליהוו חילוף
שבע שנין *leihavei chiluf sheva shanin*, should be an exchange of the
seven years of silence that I had accepted upon myself דאמר לי
רב *de-amar li Rav*, or that רב *Rav* had imposed upon me,
דאמר לי רב *de-amar li Rav*, that רב *Rav* had imposed on
me. קם אכרעיה *Kam akreiei*, he got up on his feet. אמר
ליה נהדר מר ברישא *Amar lei nehader mar be-reisha*, he said, could
you please חזר *chazer* the first thing you were saying today? So
אמר שמעתתא *amar shmaitata*, he went back, he told over the first
teaching רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan *Rabbi Yochanan*, ואקשיה *ve-akshyei*, and he challenged
it. So he kept on challenging everything all over again. אותביה בדרא
קמא *Otvei be-dara kama*, so they put him to the first row.
אמר שמעתתא ואקשיה *Amar shmaitata ve-akshyei*, and then he kept on challenging.
So what are you going to do more to show how important
he is, right? So ורבי יוחנן הוה יתיב אשבע בסתרקי *ve-Rabbi Yochanan
hava yativ a-sheva bastarkei*, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan *Rabbi Yochanan* was sitting
on seven pillars. שלפי ליה חדא בסתרקא מתותיה *Shalfei lei chada bastarka
mi-tutei*. So they removed one pillar from under him. אמר שמעתתא *Amar
shmaitata*, he told another, you know, סוגיא *sugya* over, ואקשיה ליה *ve-akshyei
lei*, and רב כהנא Rav Kahana *Rav Kahana* challenged again. עד דשלפי
ליה כולהו בסתרקי מתותיה *Ad de-shalfei lei kulehu bastarkei mi-tutei* until all
the
pillars were removed from underneath him. עד דיתיב אארעא *Ad de-yativ a-ar'a*
and he was
sitting on the ground. Now רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan גברא סבא הוה
*Rabbi Yochanan
gavra saba hava*, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan *Rabbi Yochanan* was very old,
ומסרחי גביניי *u-mesarchi gevinei*, and
his eyelashes were very long. His eyebrows- no, eyelashes, no, eyelashes were
very long. אמר להו *Amar lehu*, so he said, דלו לי עיניי
*delu li einai*,
lift up my eyes, like you know, lift up my eyelashes so
my eyelids will be lifted, ואחזיה *ve-achzyei*, and then I could see
him. דלו ליה במכחלתא דכספא *Delu lei be-machalta de-chaspa*, they lifted it
up to him with like silver tongs. So by the way, what's
his name from YU,
what's the name of the guy that does the academic Talmud in
the Babylonian context of the גמרא *Gemara*, Elman, Yaakov Elman points out
that here they're telling a story about רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan. *Rabbi
Yochanan* that lives in ארץ ישראל *Eretz Yisrael*, but they're telling it
totally through this Persian, like this Babylonian lens of these like stories,
you know, because in the Babylonian stories or whatever, you know, the-
like the ruler or whatever it is, is this big heavy guy
and he's sitting on these- all of these pillars and he has
these long eyelashes that are being lifted up with silver tongs. Apparently,
it's like a trope, you know, in terms of like these Babylonian
stories and now it's being read onto רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan *Rabbi
Yochanan* who's living in ארץ ישראל *Eretz Yisrael*. The whole idea that
tends to be that in the גמרא בבלי *Gemara Bavli*, they imagine
the ישיבות *yeshivos* in ארץ ישראל *Eretz Yisrael* are through a Babylonian
lens, but here even though just the whole visuals are very Babylonian.
Anyway, okay. So אמר ליה רבי יוחנן *amar lei Rabbi
Yochanan*, okay, so they lifted up his eyelids. חזא דפרטיה שפוותיה *Chaza
de-partiei siffvatiei*. They saw that רב כהנא's Rav Kahana *Rav Kahana's* lips
were split. סבר *Savar*, that was just a physical condition he had,
but he thought, רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* saw it, אחוכא במחייך ביה
*achucha be-machaiech bei*, he was laughing at him, that רב כהנא Rav
Kahana, *Rav Kahana* was mocking him. So חלש דעתיה *chalash da'atiei*, רבי
יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* felt despondent. He was like- that he was so
pained that this תלמיד *talmid* now was mocking him. וניח נפשיה *ve-nach
nafshei*, so not רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*, of course רבי יוחנן *Rabbi
Yochanan* feeling down caused רב כהנא Rav Kahana *Rav Kahana* to die.
Okay, that was the
punishment. Yeah, you see since he went into- maybe- maybe רב *Rav*
anticipated this or something. So it's sort of like רב כהנא Rav
Kahana *Rav Kahana* went into גלות Galus *galus*, the irony of going
into גלות *galus* is going into ארץ ישראל *Eretz Yisrael*. Okay, he
went into גלות *galus* because he didn't really keep the terms of
the גלות *galus*, he wound up dying as a result.
No, but also, he broke the guy's neck. Right.
This is ultimate- I know, that's right. He killed somebody, he went
into גלות *galus*. What do you do by killing? You go into
גלות *galus*, okay, and as a result of not keeping the terms
of the גלות *galus*, in the end רב כהנא *Rav Kahana* died.
So there seems to be some, yes, paying back for killing this
guy that רב *Rav* was not totally happy with what רב כהנא
*Rav Kahana* had done.
Right, like if he had followed that silence, he would have been
protected.
Yes, then- then his punishment would have been seven years, because also,
it's- to not be able to engage in תורה Torah *Torah* would
have been a real, you know, not just geographic גלות *galus* for
רב כהנא *Rav Kahana*, it would have been a real... Your punishment
for רב כהנא.
And an atonement. Right, exactly.
But because he didn't, then there wasn't a real גלות and then
this was the consequence. That seems to be the point. Okay, but
yes, but it's this idea that when a רב is angry at
somebody that can result in that person's death is a common trope
also in rabbinic literature.
Which they describe in a sense also רב כהנא's downfall because if
he had, you know, it might have been his pride that made
him feel he had to do this.
Maybe, that could be. That could
be. Okay, he wakes... right, he has to get up like before
he got up. Did it say before he was קם כהרי? Kam
Kahare? No, it didn't use that phrase. It just says he broke
his neck. But the same thing like you got to get up
and do something about it. That's interesting. Okay, so למחר the next
day, אמר ליה רבי יוחנן לרבנן, Amar leh Rabbi Yochanan l'rabbanan, רבי
יוחנן said to the rabbis. חזיתו לבבלאי היכי עבד, Chazitu l'bavla'ei heichi
avad, do you see how that Babylonian treated me? He's not feeling
bad that he's dead, that רב כהנא's dead. Did you see what
he... how he treated me! אמרו ליה, Amru leh, they said to
him, דהכי אורחיה, De'hachi orchiei, well that was just his normal way
he looks. That's, you know, the way he talks. It's a physical
condition. So oh my god he realized that he wasn't being מקפיד,
makpid, he realized he did the wrong thing, רבי יוחנן. אזל לגבי
מערתא, Azal l'gabbei ma'arta, so he went to the cave
where רב כהנא was
buried. חזא דהדרא ליה עכנא, Chaza d'hadra leh achna, he saw
that there was a snake that was protecting the cave and what
we're going to see in a minute the image, the snake eating
its own tail which I think is also like a very more
Persian or oriental type of an image. Okay, I don't think you're
allowed to say oriental anymore. Okay more Persian type of an image.
Okay, אמר ליה, so he said to it, עכנא עכנא, Achna achna,
snake, snake, פתח פומך, Ptach pumach, open up your mouth, ויכנס הרב
אצל תלמיד, V'yikaness harav eitzel talmid, and let the master enter in
to the student. ולא פתח, V'lo ptach, the snake wouldn't open up
its mouth.
ויכנס חבר אצל חבר, V'yikaness chaver eitzel chaver, let one colleague go
and greet his other colleague. ולא פתח, V'lo ptach, the snake didn't
open up its mouth. ויכנס תלמיד אצל הרב, V'yikaness talmid eitzel harav,
let the student... he's calling himself a student to רב כהנא... enter
and greet the רב. פתח ליה, Ptach leh, he opened it up.
So it's so funny even though רב כהנא sort of suffered this
and I think there's some sense of justly punishment or whatever, nevertheless
underscoring the idea that רב כהנא was such a greater, you know,
תורה Torah sage than רבי יוחנן. בעי רחמי, Ba'ei rachamei, but רבי
יוחנן still had powers. So רבי יוחנן prayed for him, ואוקמיה, V'ukmeih,
and he revived him even though he had died. Okay, I guess
if he could cause him to die he could cause him to
come back to life. אמר ליה, he... so רבי יוחנן said to
him, אי הוה ידענא דדרכיה דמר הכי, Ei hava yadana d'dorcheih d'mar
hachi, if I had known that that was just your normal, you
know, way, that was like a physical condition, לא חלשא דעתי, Lo
chalsha da'ati, I would not have been despondent. Like he never really
directly said he... by the way it's also interesting, right, רב כהנא
willfully caused somebody's death, you know, and here he, you know, unintentionally.
One also wonders, it's just occurring to me now, this idea of
דהכי אורחיה, De'hachi orchiei, you know the guy who was being forced
to show the grain also to some degree was not totally doing
it of his own will, you know he might not have had
a gun to his head, but to some degree he was being
compelled by circumstances right, so the same way רבי יוחנן sort of
oh had I known that was you couldn't really control it I
wouldn't have reacted this way, you could sort of wonder to reimpose
that on the earlier case with the way רב כהנא acted. Anyway
he says השתא ליתי מר בהדן, Hashta leitei mar bahadan, come back
with me back to the ישיבה. Yeshiva. אמר ליה, so רב כהנא,
you know, says what is it fool me once shame on me,
so kill me once shame on me... no kill me once shame
on you, kill me twice shame on
me. Okay. אמר ליה, אי מצית למיבעי רחמי דתו לא שכיבנא, Ei
mazit l'miba'ei rachamei d'tu lo shchivna, if you'll pray to God that
I won't die again, I don't know if that means ever or
as a result of things you do, אזלינא, Azlina, I'll go with
you, ואי לא, V'ei lo, but if you're not... you can't insure
me that this won't happen again, לא אזלינא, Lo azlina, I won't
go with you. חלף שעתא חלף שעתא, Chalaf sha'ata chalaf sha'ata, you
know once... you...
miracles only happen... you know, you know when a miracle happened once,
that was one good opportunity that you brought me back to life,
you can't promise me it's not going to happen again, I'm not
going to go. Okay. תיהא, Teihe, he woke him up... it's so
funny he was already talking to him but whatever he further revived
him, אוקמיה, Ukmeih, he stood him up, כל ספיקא דהוה ליה, Kol
sefeika d'hava leh, and רבי יוחנן asked רב כהנא all the questions
רבי יוחנן had never resolved for himself, ופשטינהו ניהליה, U'pashitinhu nihaleih, and
רב כהנא was able to answer them all for רבי יוחנן. היינו
דאמר רבי יוחנן, Heinu d'amar Rabbi Yochanan, that's רבי יוחנן says יוחנא
אמרי, Yochana amri, when you say you the בני ארץ ישראל, Bnei
Eretz Yisrael, you think the תורה Torah is
ours, דילהון היא, D'lehon hi, it really is the תורה Torah of
בבל. They really know the תורה better than we do. Okay, that's
the end of that story. Of course leaves very fascinating questions...
remind me are we reading the תלמוד בבלי... Talmud Bavli...
yeah, yeah exactly... you couldn't tell from the way that story concludes.
Alright.